Finding Aid for Morton S. Hilbert papers, 1943-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Morton S. Hilbert papers 1943-1999
Hilbert, Morton S.
07183 Aa 2
Public health professional best known for being a co-founder of Earth Day, worked in the United States and abroad as a consultant; was a University of Michigan Public Health professor. The collection includes consulting research, teaching materials, and speeches and reports.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Stephanie M. Hilbert (donor no. 8845 ) in 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
As a dedicated and determined public health professional, Morton S. Hilbert worked towards the promotion and protection of environmental health. His most well-known accomplishment is the co-founding of Earth Day. With the U.S. Public Health Service, Hilbert organized the Human Ecology Symposium in 1968. This forum helped to inform students about grave threats to environmental health in the 1960s and 70s and ultimately it inspired them to take action. In 1970 their efforts, along with a federal proclamation from U.S. Senator Gaylord Nelson, culminated in the observance of the first Earth Day.
In 1940, Hilbert graduated from the University of California, Berkeley with a bachelor's degree in civil engineering and began his career as a public health official and field engineer in Michigan. Shortly thereafter, Hilbert enrolled in the University of Michigan School of Public Health and in 1946 he received his masters degree. Hilbert then held a variety of positions and worked both in the United States and abroad. Through his consulting business, Hilbert worked in many different locations including the Virgin Islands, Thailand, and Egypt.
Throughout his career, Hilbert also served as president of a variety of state and local public health organizations such as the Michigan Public Health Association and the Engineering Society of Detroit. He was elected president of the American Public Health Association in 1976 and focused his tenure on promoting the importance of prevention, rather than corrective action, in managing environmental health.
In 1961, Morton Hilbert returned to the University of Michigan School of Public Health teaching a variety of courses. In 1968, as full professor, he was named chair of the newly created Department of Environmental Health and Industrial Health. Here his focus was in providing students with the management and planning skills necessary to implement successful environmental health projects. In1986, Hilbert retired from the University of Michigan; he continued working as a private consultant and served as the Director of the European Office for the National Sanitation Foundation (NSF) from 1986 until about 1991. He died at his home in Bellevue, Washington in 1998.
The Morton S. Hilbert papers document various aspects of environmental health and include materials related to Hilbert's teaching and consulting careers. They are comprised of four series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Subject Files, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Earth Day.; Environmental health.; Hilbert, Morton S.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Photographs.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers series includes awards, biographical sketches, and resumes that span Hilbert's lifetime. Materials related to Earth Day consist of newspaper articles about the event and Hilbert's involvement in establishing it, and a photograph of those who participated in the founding seminar. Also included in the series, are materials related to Hilbert's brief involvement with the University of Washington.
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketches (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Earth Day (Box 1)
  - Resumes (Box 1)
  - University of Washington (Box 1)
- Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series consists of research related to Hilbert's activities as a private consultant in various international locations; extensive lecture notes and course outlines that Hilbert created as a professor of environmental health; and numerous speeches, reports, and articles by Hilbert on a range of environmental health concerns.
  - Consulting Activities
    - Eastern Europe (Box 1)
    - European Community (Box 1)
    - Foreign Service (Box 1)
    - NSF Europe
      - Contacts (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Standards (Box 1)
      - Vessel Sanitation Inspection Program (Box 1)
    - Virgin Islands (Box 1)
  - Speeches, Reports, and Articles
    - 1950s (Box 1)
    - 1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
    - 1990s (Box 1)
    - Inaugural Address, President of the American Public Health Association October 18, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Teaching Materials
    - University of Michigan
      - Environmental Health Administration and Analysis (Box 2)
      - Environmental Health Planning and Program Administration (Box 2)
      - Introductory Environmental Health (Box 2)
    - University of Minnesota
      - Environmental Health Administration (Box 2)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files series contains clippings, pamphlets, and reports that Hilbert gathered and used as a reference collection. These materials document environmental health issues of the 1940s-1990s and address general concerns around education and leadership.
  - Aluminum, Safety of (Box 2)
  - Cruise Ships, Health Aspects of (Box 2)
  - Detroit, Environmental Health Program for (Box 2)
  - Economic Growth, Environmental Impact of (Box 2)
  - Energy Sources, Environmental Impact of (Box 2)
  - Environmental Health Concerns, General (Box 2)
  - Epidemiology (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of Health Programs (Box 2)
  - Fatalistic Perspectives on the Environment (Box 2)
  - Federal Government Policy on the Environment (Box 2)
  - Food Safety (Box 2)
  - Group Work, General and Public Health-specific (Box 3)
  - Relationship between Health Insurance and Environmental Policy (Box 3)
  - Hollywood and Environmentalism (Box 3)
  - Housing, Health Impact of (Box 3)
  - Industrial Health (Box 3)
  - International Environmental Health (Box 3)
  - International Markets, Environmental Impact of (Box 3)
  - Management Techniques, General (Box 3)
  - Microwaves, Safety of (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Power, Environmental Impact of (Box 3)
  - Occupational Health (Box 3)
  - Planning Strategies, General and Public Health-specific (Box 3)
  - Pollution, General (Box 3)
  - Population, Health Impact of (Box 3)
  - Prevention as Environmental Health Strategy (Box 3)
  - Public Health Administration (Box 3)
  - Research Methods and Results, General and Public Health-specific (Box 3)
  - Rodents, Health Impact of (Box 3)
  - Solid Waste, Health Impact of (Box 3)
  - Teaching Techniques, General (Box 3)
  - Toxic Metabolism (Box 3)
  - Training Needs and Practices, General and Public Health-specific (Box 3)
  - Urban Environment, Health Impact of (Box 3)
  - Water Pollution (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes a DVD containing two programs produced by Stephanie Hilbert (Morton's wife) in 1978. They feature Morton Hilbert speaking on the topics of environmental health and the importance of food safety. Also included in the series are two photographs of professional meetings.
  - Educational Programs featuring Morton Hilbert, DVD (Box 3)
  - Photographs: Morton Hilbert at Professional Meetings (Box 3)